A Guide to the Nelson A. Rockefeller personal papers, Washington, DC, Series O FA350
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Special Committee on Government Organization (SCOGO), Reorganization Advisory Committee (RAC), President's Advisory Committee on Government Organization (PACGO), November 1952-December 1958; 5; 14.8 Cubic Feet; 12 document boxes 67 bound volumes
  - President's Advisory Committee on Government Organization (PACGO), November 1952-December 1958; O_5C
    - Covering Letter and Findings - NAR Memo to President, 1953 (Box 50, Folder 449)
    - Formation and Clearances, 1952 (Box 50, Folder 450)
    - Post Office, 1953 (Box 50, Folder 451)
    - Removal of Papers, 1959 (Box 51, Folder 452)
    - General, 1956-1961 (Box 51, Folder 453)
    - Defense Advisory Committee, 1956 (Box 51, Folder 454)
    - Clippings, 1952-1953 (Box 51, Folder 455)
    - Clippings, 1952-1953 (Box 51, Folder 456)
    - Temple University Survey of Government
      - Organization - General, 1952-1953 (Box 51, Folder 457)
      - Information Bulletins, 1952 (Box 51, Folder 458)
      - Foreign Affairs, Research Studies, 1953 (Box 52, Folder 459)
      - Major Problems Under Study (Box 52, Folder 460)
      - Policy Formation and Execution (Box 52, Folder 461)
      - Presidency and Staff Agencies (Box 52, Folder 462)
      - Fiscal Agencies (Box 52, Folder 463)
      - Accounting (Box 52, Folder 464)
      - Personnel (Box 52, Folder 465)
      - Foreign Affairs (Box 53, Folder 466)
      - Defense (Box 53, Folder 467)
      - Natural Resources (Box 53, Folder 468)
      - Agriculture (Box 53, Folder 469)
      - Agriculture (Box 53, Folder 470)
      - Post Office (Box 53, Folder 471)
      - Business Enterprise (Box 53, Folder 472)
      - Labor (Box 54, Folder 473)
      - Social Security Adminstration (Box 54, Folder 474)
      - Veterans Administration (Box 54, Folder 475)
      - Federal-State Relations (Box 54, Folder 476)
      - Atomic Energy Commission (Box 54, Folder 477)
      - Regulatory Commissions (Box 54, Folder 478)
      - Publications - Brookings Institute Studies of Executive Office of the President (Box 54, Folder 479)
    - Hoover Commission - Digest of Recommendations, 1949 (Box 54, Folder 480)
    - Publications (Box 55, Folder 480A)
    - Publications (Box 55, Folder 480B)
    - Publications (Box 55, Folder 480C)
    - Publications (Box 55, Folder 480D)
    - Publications (Box 55, Folder 480E)
    - Publications (Box 56, Folder 480F)
    - Publications (Box 56, Folder 480G)
    - Publications (Box 56, Folder 480H)
    - Publications (Box 56, Folder 480I)
    - Publications (Box 56, Folder 480J)
    - President's Advisory Committee on Government Organization (PACGO) Bound Volumes, 1949-1958
      - Establishment and Progress Reports (Volume 1)
        Scope and contents note
        A. Establishment of Committee: Executive Order 10432, January 24, 1953; B. Role and Purpose and first program of Committee; C. Herbert Hoover Comments on 1953 recommendations; D. Proposed public Presidential statements on Plans (Lubell Summaries); E. Clearance of Documents Prior to Submission to President; F. Administration and Delegations of PACGO; G. Progress Reports (November 1953 - September 1957); H. Nelson Rockefeller's Resignation, with his Final Report to President, December 29, 1958; I. President's Letter to Mr. Rockefeller, December 29, 1958.
      - Agendas, Schedules, 1953-1958 (Volume 2)
        A. Agenda - January-April 1953; B. Schedule for Committee: January-April 1953; C. Mr. Rockefeller's calendar: February-April 1953; D. Agenda - November and December 1953; E. Agenda - 1954; F. Agenda - 1955; G. Agenda - 1956; H. Agenda - 1957; I. Agenda - 1958.
      - Minutes, 1953-1958 (Volume 3)
        A. 1953 (November and December); B. 1953; C. 1954; D. 1955; E. 1956; F. 1957; G. 1958.
      - Budget and Staff, 1953-1959 (Volume 4)
        A. Allocations to Committee Fiscal Year 1953; B. Budget and Appropriations FY 1954 and 1955; C. Budget and Appropriation FY 1956; D. Budget and Appropriation - FY 1957; E. Budget and Appropriation FY 1958; F. Budget and Appropriation FY 1959; G. Staff - 1952 and Spring of 1953; H. Staff - Permanent Committee Staff, 1953 and subsequent; I. Arthur A. Kimball, Staff Director; J. Rank of GS-18 for Mr. Arthur A. Kimball; K. Miscellaneous Correspondence from Mr. Kimball.
      - Appropriations Hearings: House and Senate, 1954-1959 (Volume 5)
        A. Senate Hearings for FY 1954 & 1955; B. Senate & House Hearings, FY 1956; C. Senate & House Hearings, FY 1957; D. Senate & House Hearings, FY 1958; E. Senate & House Hearings, FY 1959.
      - U.S. Government Organization Manual (Volume 6)
      - Temple University Reports, 1953 (Volume 7)
        In the preface of the Temple University Report of 1953, on Survey of Federal Reorganization, it states that in October of 1953, "a group of public-spirited citizens gave support to the Temple University Survey in order to bring the Hoover Report up to date and prepare guidelines for continued reorganization in the new Administration."
        A. Papers on policy matters with respect to the work of Temple University;B. Task Force Report and studies of Temple University: 1. Business Enterprises; 2. Independent Agencies; 3. Organization of Emergency Functions; 4. Challenge List; 5. Miscellaneous correspondence re progress of various surveys;C. Report of Temple University: Survey of Federal Reorganization.
      - Reorganization Act, Plans and Programs, 1949-1957 (Volume 8)
        A. Reorganization Act of 1949 (as amended through September 4, 1957); B. Governor Adams' Request to Departments and Agencies: February 5, 1953, on overlapping responsibilities; C. Reorganization Plans - 1953 through 1958; D. Review for Possible Action of 1953 Recommendations; E. Reorganization Program for 1954; F. Reorganization Program for 1955; G. Reorganization Program for 1956; H. Reorganization Possibilities for 1957.
      - Recommendations Approved by the President, 1953 (Volume 9)
        The memoranda in this volume are copies of plans submitted to and approved by the President. A. Committee's memoranda approved by President. Under "miscellaneous" in the index under Tab A are the memoranda submitted to the President but not acted upon.B. Summary of Actions Required on Committee's recommendations, with status noted as of December 11, 1953. The summary sheet for each memorandum indicates an approved date, which is the date the memoranda themselves were approved by the President.
      - Final Recommendations to the President, 1953 (Volume 10)
        The memoranda in this volume incorporate the changes resulting from Presidential conferences. The dates on the memoranda are when the recommendations were approved by the President. They were presented to him in final form on April 22, 1953.
      - Hoover Commission Reports: Status, 1949-1953 (Volume 11)
        A. Senate Action on Reports: January 9, 1953; B. Bureau of the Budget Status Reports on Recommendations: December 1952; C. Citizens Committee Releases on Status of Reports.
      - Hoover Commission Reports: Part 1, 1949 (Volume 12)
        Concluding Report (A Report to the Congress); General Management of the Executive Branch; Personnel Management; Office of General Services Supply Activities; The Post Office; Foreign Affairs; Department of Agriculture; Budgeting and Accounting; The National Security Organization.
      - Hoover Commission Reports: Part 2, 1949 (Volume 13)
        Veterans Affairs; Department of Commerce; Treasury Department; Regulatory Commissions; Department of Labor;Department of the Interior; Social Security: Education Indian Affairs; Medical Activities; Overseas Administration; Federal-State Relations; Federal Research; Federal Business Enterprises.
      - Hoover Commission Reports: Appendices - Part I (Task Force Reports), 1949 (Volume 14)
        Scop and contents note
        Appendix: A. Federal Personnel; B. The Federal Supply System; C. Records Management; D. Statistical Agencies; E. Departmental Management; F. Fiscal, Budgeting, and Accounting Activities; G. National Security Organization; H. Foreign Affairs; I. The Post Office; J. Revolving Funds and Business Enterprises of the Government; K. Water Resources Projects.
      - Hoover Commission Reports: Appendices: Part II (Task Force Reports), 1949 (Volume 15)
        Appendix: L. Natural Resources; M. Agriculture Activities; N. Regulatory Commissions; O. Federal Medical Services; P. Public Welfare; Q. Public Works; R. Lending Agencies.
      - Hoover Commission Reports: Part 1, 1955 (Volume 16)
        Index: Final Report to the Congress; Progress Report (Dec. 31, 1954); Budget and Accounting; Business Enterprises; Business Organization of the Department of Defense; Depot Utilization.
      - Hoover Commission Reports: Part 2, 1955 (Volume 17)
        Federal Medical Services; Food and Clothing; Intelligence Activities; Legal Services and Procedure; Lending Agencies; Overseas Economic Operations; Paperwork Management, Part I; Paperwork Management, Part II.
      - Hoover Commission Reports: Part 3, 1955 (Volume 18)
        Personnel and Civil Service; Real Property Management; Research and Development; Surplus Property; Transportation; Water Resources and Power, Vol. 1; Water Resources and Power, Vol. 2.
      - Hoover Commission Reports: Task Force Reports: Part 1, 1955 (Volume 19)
        Budget and Accounting; Business Enterprises (Outside of the Department of Defense); Business Enterprises (of the Department of Defense); Special Personnel Problems; Military Procurement; Depot Utilization; Federal Medical Services; Food and Clothing.
      - Hoover Commission Reports: Task Force Reports: Part 2, 1955 (Volume 20)
        Legal Services and Procedure; Lending Agencies; Overseas Economic Operations.
      - Hoover Commission Reports, 1955 - Task Force Reports - Part 3 (Volume 21)
        Paperwork Management, Part I; Paperwork Management, Part II; Personnel and Civil Service; Real Property Management; Research Activities; Surplus Property; Transportation.
      - Hoover Commission Reports, 1955 - Task Force Reports - Part 4 (Volume 22)
        Water Resources and Power, Volumes 1, 2, and 3.
      - Second Hoover Commission: Establishment (Volume 23)
        A. Establishment, Membership and Scope of Activities (with Citizens' Committee Press Releases); B. Digests and Analyses of Reports by Citizens Committee; C. Press Clippings re Reports of Hoover Commission.
      - Second Hoover Commission: Staff Analysis and Progress Part I (Volume 24)
        A. Staff Analysis and Progress on Reports General; B. Budget and Accounting; C. Business Enterprises; D. Business Organization - Defense Department; E. Federal Medical Services; F. Food and Clothing; G. Independent Agencies; H. Intelligence Activities; I. Legal Services and Procedure; J. Lending Agencies; K. Overseas Economic Operations; L. Paperwork Management.
      - Second Hoover Commission: Staff Analysis and Progress Part 2 (Volume 25)
        A. Personnel and Civil Service - General; Personnel and Civil Service - Senior Civil Service; C. Real Property Management; D. Research and Development; E. Surplus Property; F. Transportation; G. Water Resources and Power.
      - Second Hoover Commission: Implementation (Volume 26)
        A. Organization Committee Recommendations to President and B. Policy Committee (Kestnbaum) Recommendations to President.
      - White House: 1953 Recommendations (Volume 27)
        A. Background and Organization Chart; B. Memorandum No. 2, approved by President January 3, 1953; C. Memorandum No. 2 - Supplement (Drafts & Related Memoranda); D. Memorandum No. 2 - Final; E. Memoranda to President-Elect Eisenhower: Chairman, Civil Service Commission (Dec. 4, 1952), Science Advisory Committee (Dec. 17, 1952), Commission on Loyalty and Security (Dec. 21, 1952), Telecommunications Problems; F. National Security Council; G. Council of Economic Advisers; H. ODM-NSRB Merger (Note: See volume on Civil Defense for merger with ODM in 1958); I. Temple University Survey (by McKinsey & Co.) - Jan. 2, 1953, with Budget & other comments; J. Temple University Survey on the Executive Offices, March 30, 1953.
      - White House: Organization Part 1 (Volume 28)
        A. Background to Making a Study of White House; B. Presidential Workload and Possible Delegations; C. President Hoover and Senator Kennedy Proposals for a second Vice President; D. Administrative Vice President (1956 draft proposal).
      - White House: Organization Part 2 (Volume 29)
        A. Proposals for Office of Administration and, later, Office of Management (1957) and B. Proposal for Executive Office for Organization and Management Activities (1958).
      - White House: Miscellaneous Agencies and Functions (Volume 30)
        A. Accounting - Temple University Survey, 1953; B. Commission on Intergovernmental Relations; C. Consolidated Government Travel Agency - Proposal; D. Point 4 Program for Depressed Areas of U.S. - Proposal; E. Public Works Planning - Coordinator; F. Independent Agencies; G. Telecommunications - 1953 Proposal; H. Telecommunications - Establishment of Cabinet Committee; I. Telecommunications - Proceedings of Cabinet Committee, with Interim Report of June 3, 1955, and subsequent correspondence.
      - Personnel Organization and Management, 1953-1957 (Volume 31)
        1953 Proposals: A. Temple University Survey Report, Dec. 31, 1953 (Presented to President Jan. 3, 1953); B. Background papers, as follow (written in early 1953): Information re appointments to and removals from positions, Proposed Executive Pay Schedule, Riders (restrictive) which have been dropped or revoked, and Riders (restrictive) now in effect; C. Drafts and Related Memoranda; D. Final Report to the President; E. Implementation of Report; F. Conference on Administrative Procedure - Report of April 29, 1953.1954-1955: G. Federal Wage Boards - Proposed Reorganization Plan.1956-1957: H. Bureau of Personnel Management, White House; I. President's Action - Special Assistant to the President for Personnel Management - Sept. 16, 1957.
      - Personnel - Overseas, 1954-1956 (Volume 32)
        A. Study by Philip Young, with report to Cabinet, December 15, 1954; B. The Wriston Report, May 18, 1954; C. Proposed Recommendation, with clearances from agencies (for an International Service Act); D. Draft Legislation, Jan. 1956 - International Service Act; E. Actions Taken to Implement a Coordinated Overseas Personnel System (principally ICA and USIA).
      - Science and Space, 1952-1958 (Volume 33)
        A. Science Advisory Committee memorandum, Dec. 17, 1952, concerning the role of science in government; B. Study by PACGO on Coordination of Government Scientific Research Activities with designation of Science Advisory Committee to do a full-scale study; C. Draft Report on Government Science Organization, Dec. 29, 1955 (recommends a reconstituted Science Advisory Committee of ODM to be put within the White House structure); D. International Science - Role of the Federal Government; E. Scientists and Engineers - Establishment of a National Committee for their development (April 3, 1956) and Report of SAC on Availability of Scientific Info. (December 7, 1958); F. Basic Scientific Research - Role of National Science Foundation; G. Science Advisory Committee report on improvement and strengthening of American Science (Sept. 19, 1958) with President's approval of Dec. 28, 1958; H. SPACE Agency - Establishment in 1958.
      - Loyalty and Security, 1952-1956 (Volume 34)
        Part I. Administration's Loyalty and Security PoliciesA. Rockefeller recommendation to President-elect, Dec. 21, 1952; B. John Lockwood's recommendation for Mr. Rockefeller (1954) for establishment of a Commission; C. Gordon Gray's Proposal for a "Royal Commission"; D. The Finder Proposal for a Presidential Commission on American Principles and Individual Liberties; E. Congressional establishment (1955) of a Commission on Government Security; F. Administration Policy paper, February 17, 1955: "A Uniform Clearance Program for Individuals other than full-time Federal Employees who Require access to U.S. classified information"; G. Loyalty Review Board (Hirman Bingham, Chairman): Report to FBI & Attorney General 2/6/53 (w/Mr. Rockefeller's memorandum of March 25, 1955); H. American Veterans Committee release on security program (4/6/1955).
        Part II. Unclassified Research - Loyalty (Note: Refer to HEW Vol. 17 for period prior to Nov. 1954):I. Study by Rockefeller Committee (with related draft memoranda); J. Final papers establishing study: Rockefeller & Hughes to Gov. Adams, Dec. 16, 1954, Gov. Adams to Dr. Bronk of National Academy of Science, Jan. 11, 1955 (with related correspondence); K. Establishment of Study group by National Academy of Science; L. Report by National Academy of Science - March 13, 1956 (w/ Gov. Adams' public reply of August 14, 1956).
      - Federal Civil Defense Administration Part 1, 1953-1957 (Volume 35)
        A. Background, drafts and related memoranda in connection with 1953 recommendations; B. Final Recommendation to President, April 11, 1953; C. FCDA Delegation of Authority to Departments and Agencies (see recommendation No. 10 in Tab B); D. Holifield Bill (1954) to establish FCDA into a Cabinet Department; E. Establishment of Civil Defense Coordinating Board, May 11, 1955; F. University Contract to study Civil Defense Research (1955); G. FCDA Report - Proposal for Cabinet Department (assignment of study to PACGO July 29, 1955); H. General David Sarnoff's Paper on Civil Defense Planning (Aug. 1955); I. Organizational Developments of FCDA, and preliminary study of proposal (Jan. 1956) to transfer FCDA to the Executive Office of the President; J. Study on proposal for Cabinet Status for FCDA (includes Congressional bills to establish a Federal Department) 1956 & early 1957; K. Budget study (Feb. 1956, revised Dec. 3, 1956) on organization of FCDA, with staff comments; L. Draft Proposal for merger of FCDA & HHFA (early 1957) Department of Urban Affairs (see also Volume 37); M. Rockefeller Committee Proposal for a study of civil defense measures (see also Volume 36) - April 1957; N. Department of Urban Affairs - Further correspondence on Proposal - May-Sept., 1957; O. Mr. Rockefeller's speeches on the subject of civil defense measures and urban affairs.
      - Federal Civil Defense Administration Part 2, 1955-1958 (Volume 36)
        A. Merger of FCDA and ODM - Proposal, with drafts and final papers of recommendations (Oct. 10, 1957-April, 1958); B. Merger of FCDA and ODM - Office of Civil and Defense Mobilization Executive Order, July 1, 1958; Reorganization Plan No. 1 of 1958 (April 24, 1958); C. OCDM - The National Plan for Civil Defense and Defense Mobilization; D. FCDA Program - Organization for Post-Attack (August 9, 1955 through 1957).
      - Atomic Energy Commission (AEC); General Services Administration (GSA); Housing and Home Finance Agency (HHFA), 1953-1956 (Volume 37)
        A. Committee Recommendations on AEC, 1953, with drafts and related memoranda; B. Euratom (See Special Assistant files on Atomic Energy); C. Organizational Problems in AEC, Budget Study - Dec. 7, 1956,Brookings Institution study, Dec. 1956; D. AEC-ICA Roles in Foreign Atoms for Peace Program (see Brookings Institution study in Tab C), Special Assistant files on Atomic Energy; E. GSA - Committee recommendations in 1953 with related background papers; F. GSA - Correspondence subsequent to 1953 recommendations; G. HHFA - Committee recommendations in 1953 with related background papers; H. HHFA - Proposed Reorganization Plan, 1954; I. HHFA: Committee action in 1955 calling for study on Housing (includes thoughts from Aksel Nielsen); J. HHFA - Proposal (1956) for cabinet status of HHFA (see Vol. 35 for Proposed Department of Urban Affairs - merger of FCDA & HHFA).
      - Departments of Agriculture, Justice, and Labor, 1953-1956 (Volume 38)
        A. Agriculture - Background study papers, 1953 committee recommendation; B. Agriculture - Senate Bill (January 26, 1953); C. Agriculture - Drafts and related memoranda of report; D. Agriculture - Final Recommendation to President, 1953; E. Agriculture - Reorganization Plan No. 2 of 1953 with Senate and House Hearings; F. Justice - Committee recommendations of 1953 to President (drafts and background); G. Justice - Final Recommendation to President, 1953; H. Justice - Reorganization Plan No. 4 of 1953; I. Labor - Background study papers, 1953 committee recommendations; J. Labor - Temple U. draft reports, with Budget comments; K. Labor - Draft memos, and related memoranda; L. Labor - Final Recommendation to President, 1953; M. Farm Labor Service; N. Field Office Organization - Labor; O. Labor Dept. meeting with Committee, December 1956, with paper entitled "Labor Aspects of Economic Aid."
      - Department of Commerce, 1953-1956 (Volume 40)
        A. Background to committee recommendations with drafts and related memoranda, 1953; B. Temple University Report with Jessee Jones Comments, Dec. 30, 1953; C. Committee's recommendation to President - March 14, 1953; D. Reorganization Plan No. 10 of 1953 (airline subsidies) with House hearings; E. Government Patents Board - 1953 study; F. Small Business Administration (old Small Defense Plants Adm) background for study, drafts and related memoranda, 1953; G. Committee's recommendation to President on SPDA, March 14, 1953; H. Studies subsequent to 1953 re transfer of SBA to Commerce, and Cabinet Committee Report on Small Business (1956).
      - Transportation, 1953 (Volume 40)
        A. 1953 Studies.Cabinet Committee on Transportation: B. Establishment of Cabinet Committee with background study by Ernest Williams; C. Staff of Cabinet Committee; D. Correspondence re study by Cabinet Committee; E. Report of Cabinet Committee, December 8, 1954, with Presidential Message - January, 1955; and Summary of Final Recommendations - April, 1955; F. Implementation of Recommendations of Cabinet Committee.Department of Transportation (and Commerce): G. Proposal for Department of Commerce and Transportation, with staff studies and correspondence.St. Lawrence Seaway: H. Correspondence and Executive Order relating to the supervision and direction of St. Lawrence Seaway.
      - Transportation: Aviation Facilities and Regulatory Agencies, 1953-1957 (Volume 41)
        Aviation Facilities: A. William Harding Analysis of Need for Aviation Facilities Study - February 1955; B. The Harding Study with related correspondence, and Progress Report of October 1955; C. Harding Report on Aviation Facilities - December 31, 1955; D. Curtiss Plan, May 1957, Aviation Facilities Planning with related memoranda; E. Gen. Quesada's Implementation of Curtiss Plan with Charrington Report - Federal Aviation Agency.
        Regulatory Agencies: F. 1953 Proposal - Background papers; G. Temple University Survey - with Budget comments; H. Final Report to President - April 1953; I. Subsequent correspondence re Regulatory Agencies, 1956-1957, with background paper prepared by Ernest Williams.
      - Department of Health, Education, and Welfare, 1953 (Volume 42)
        A. Bureau of the Budget Background study papers, 1953; B. Background Papers to 1953 Study of Federal Security Agency including Temple University Survey; C. Budget comments on Temple Survey (and other comments); D. Consultations and Negotiations looking toward the establishment of a new Department; E. Draft recommendations, with related memorandum, and meeting with President February 14, 1953; F. Final Recommendation to President - February 1953; G. Reorganization Plan No. 1 of 1953 (with hearings).
      - Department of the Interior, 1953-1954 (Volume 43)